So today's דף daf ס"ב, Samech Beis, we pick up on ס"א
Samech Aleph עמוד ב' Amud Beis at the two
dots, ואמורי שלמי יחיד. V'imurei Shalmei Yachid. So here's a משנה Mishna
it says we're dealing with what things get תנופה. Tenufa. We had
a whole discussion about the combination of the owners and the כהנים.
Kohanim. The תורה Torah obviously emphasizes the owners, but the גמרא Gemara
also says that the כהנים Kohanim put their hands underneath.
תוספות Tosafos dealt with as I mentioned the question about why it
wasn't a חציצה, Chatzitza, discussed whether the owners were really towards the
top rim and the כהנים Kohanim were below,
but otherwise he also suggests the כהנים Kohanim were really directly under
the owners. And what I forgot to mention yesterday is one explanation
why it isn't חציצה Chatzitza is because at the end of the
day we're still admitting that the primary person doing the תנופה Tenufa
is the owner. So even when we include also the כהן Kohen
in the תנופה. Tenufa. That's interesting for the גמרא Gemara we're about
to see, because the משנה Mishna said that whether it's a קרבן
Korban even the קרבן Korban of women gets תנופה, Tenufa, but it
says ישראל ולא באחרים. Yisrael v'lo ba'acherim.
And presumably that means Jewish קרבנות Korbanot and not non-Jews, which we
had seen before, non-Jews were discussed in terms of הגשה Hagasha and
סמיכה Semicha and לבונה Levona and so on, so it makes sense
to be relating to that idea too. Let's take a look what
the גמרא Gemara does with it. ואמורי שלמי יחיד וחזה ושוק שלהן,
V'imurei Shalmei Yachid v'Chazeh v'Shok shelahen, and
אימורים imurim of a normal private שלמים Shlamim together with the breast
and the thigh, those get waved. That's in the תורה. Torah. אחד
הנשים ואחד הנשים, Echad hanashim v'echad hanashim, whether men or a woman,
בישראל אבל לא באחרים, B'Yisrael aval lo ba'acherim, Jews but not others,
again presumably meaning non-Jews.
Basically a מומר mumar or something?
Well, maybe, but in the משנה Mishna probably means non-Jews. So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי קאמר, Mai Ka'amar, what does this mean בישראל
ולא באחרים? B'Yisrael v'lo ba'acherim? אמר
רב יהודה הכי קאמר, Amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar, this is what
it means: אחד האנשים ואחד הנשים קרבנן טעון תנופה, Echad ha'anashim v'echad
hanashim Korbanan taun Tenufa, men and women's קרבן Korban requires תנופה, Tenufa,
so you have to do תנופה Tenufa for it. However, who does
the תנופה? Tenufa? תנופת עצמה בישראל אבל לא בידי נשים, Tenufas atzmah
b'Yisrael aval lo biydei nashim, but the actual act of תנופה Tenufa
is only done with ישראל Yisrael and not with women. So besides
for all the problematic of
ישראל Yisrael does not include women, which sometimes you do have, I
mean for example, just if you have to talk about the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's an עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, the עזרת נשים
Ezras Nashim in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is not contrasted to
the עזרת גברים, Ezras Gevarim, the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim is contrasted
to the עזרת ישראל. Ezras Yisrael.
So sadly sometimes the גמרא Gemara does see ישראל Yisrael as a
contrast to נשים, Nashim, then not somehow primarily including them in that
term, which is itself obviously difficult. You know, sometimes the דרשה Drasha
is בני ישראל ולא בנות ישראל, Bnei Yisrael v'lo Bnot Yisrael, and
there at least the דרשה Drasha is on בני. Bnei. So anyway,
here it is, that's number one, which is a problem. But number
two, what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that although the משנה
Mishna says that you do תנופה Tenufa for a women's קרבן, Korban,
here it's saying that no, the קרבן Korban requires the תנופה, Tenufa,
but the women can't do it. So somehow the כהן Kohen does
it for the women. And that's particularly interesting given that although we've
introduced the כהן, Kohen, presumably the כהן's Kohen playing a secondary role
and the owners are the primary, and the תורה Torah even emphasizes
ידיו תביאנה להניף אותו, yadav taviena l'hanifo oso, his hand should bring
that sense of ownership, the owner of the קרבן Korban brings it.
So there is a ברייתא Braisa later on, it doesn't seem that
the גמרא Gemara is getting this out of, you know, just out
of thin air, there is a ברייתא Braisa later on that says
that a כהן Kohen does תנופה Tenufa for a woman's קרבן, Korban,
but it's I think still very questionable whether that's פשט p'shat in
the משנה. Mishna. The גמרא's Gemara choosing to read that as פשט
p'shat in the משנה. Mishna. No Joe, you can come near the
table here. Okay, push that, you can push that.
Come, what about they want to leave for מנחה Mincha then? Okay,
so the גמרא's Gemara going to ask exactly that question. So let's
take a look.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, so for it's a ברייתא, Braisa, בני ישראל
מניפים ואין עובדי כוכבים מניפים, Bnei Yisrael menifim v'ein ovdei kochavim menifim,
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael do תנופה Tenufa not non-Jews, בני ישראל מניפים
ואין הנשים מניפות, Bnei Yisrael menifim v'ein hanashim menifot, בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael do it and not women, the women don't do תנופה. Tenufa.
אמר רב יאשיה, Amar Rav Yoshiya, now Rav Yoshiya asked exactly Michael's
question, מצינו שחלק הכתוב בין קרבן ישראל לקרבן עובדי כוכבים לקרבן נשים
בסמיכה. matzinu she-chilek hakatuv bein Korban Yisrael l'Korban ovdei kochavim l'Korban nashim
b'Semicha.
We've seen that the script made a distinction between the קרבן Korban
of a male Jew between that of a non-Jew and between that
of women by סמיכה, Semicha, when it comes to the סמיכה, Semicha,
that we know that a woman's קרבן Korban and non-Jew's קרבן Korban
do not require סמיכה. Semicha. יכול נחלוק בתנופה, Yachol nachlok b'Tenufa,
so maybe we could distinguish also by תנופה, Tenufa, and now here
the question is not to say that somebody else does it for
the women, but to say maybe we should say that there's no
תנופה Tenufa at all done to a woman's קרבן. Korban. If we
say there's no סמיכה Semicha done, maybe we should say there's no
תנופה Tenufa done. יכול נחלוק בתנופה, Yachol nachlok b'Tenufa, לא, Lo, no.
מה לי שחלק בסמיכה שהסמיכה בבעלים, Mah li she-chilek b'Semicha she-haSemicha b'be'alim,
I can understand to say to distinguish by סמיכה Semicha because that's
only the owners, so if we say that a woman can't do
it, then nobody else should be doing it. It's either the owners
or nobody, that's the assumption by סמיכה. Semicha. סמיכה's Semicha about identifying
ownership in relationship. So if it can't be the owners, then nobody
should be doing it. Okay,
however, נחלוק בתנופה, nachlok b'Tenufa, will we also distinguish by תנופה, Tenufa,
meaning saying
that they totally doesn't get it, שתנופה בכהנים, she-Tenufa b'Kohanim, that you
even תנופה Tenufa involves כהנים Kohanim as well. So here the גמרא's
Gemara making a big difference between תנופה. Tenufa. תנופה tnufa and סמיכה.
Smicha. סמיכה Smicha is that, I mean, it's a קא דריש, ka
darish, but you could also say it as what its function is,
that סמיכה Smicha requires owners; without the owners, nothing. So if you're
going to exclude women from סמיכה, Smicha, nobody's going to do סמיכה.
Smicha. תנופה tnufa is supposed to be with the owners, but it's
supposed to also be with the כהנים. kohanim. So therefore, it's possible
to exclude women from the act and still demand תנופה tnufa on
the קרבן, korban, which is what we say the כהן kohen does
תנופה. tnufa. You can translate that into the question of the role
that the סמיכה Smicha and the תנופה tnufa is doing. סמיכה Smicha
is about symbolizing ownership, whereas תנופה tnufa is about, you know, you
could say some type of a ritual unlike any other ritual somehow,
let's say, designating it for God or, you know, it's some part
of the process of sort of הקרבה. hakrava. So even though traditionally
it involved the ישראל, Yisrael, but so many of the rituals of
הקרבה hakrava are fundamentally the כהנים, kohanim, so it's possible to imagine
the waving gets done by the כהנים kohanim and it's not about
ownership. So that's the way the גמרא Gemara is phrasing it. I
should say that, by the way, I was reading just last night
a lot of Jacob Milgrom to see what he says about all
these things, תנופה tnufa and הגשה, hagasha, and so I'll share some
of that. But what he says about סמיכה, Smicha, which is not
our focus now, he gave like a lot of different possible explanations
for סמיכה, Smicha, but he sort of feels that the one that's
most, sort of, you know, consistent with the evidence is exactly that
סמיכה Smicha is about asserting ownership. He doesn't turn to our גמרא,
Gemara, but he actually turns to the fact that there's no—what do
you not have סמיכה Smicha on? You don't have סמיכה Smicha on
a מנחה, mincha, on a קרבן korban of birds, and on a
קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. And he says why? Because a מנחה mincha
and a bird קרבן korban you could hold totally in your hand.
So the idea of ownership is not necessary; you're completely holding it.
Whereas an animal, you're walking into the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, so
you need something more to symbolize ownership. And a קרבן ציבור, korban
tzibbur, obviously if it's about ownership, there's no point in the ציבור
tzibbur קרבן korban of ownership. The ownership is this is your private
individual; you want to assert "this is my קרבן."
korban. So you can have representatives of the ציבור? tzibbur?
Right. Well, we're actually going to—well, that's true. But anyway, that's his
approach. So he very much emphasizes סמיכה Smicha as that. And that's
what the גמרא Gemara says, is that סמיכה Smicha as being done
by the owners is not being done at all. תנופה tnufa is
interesting. תנופה tnufa he says, because I was very curious because it
seems like we're now talking about all these different possible ways of
תנופה: tnufa: עומר, omer,
שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, you know, נזיר. nazir. What's going on with
all these different—what's the common denominator? חזה ושוק, chazeh veshok, etc. So
he says, I thought this was very broad, he says that, you
know, he—the תורה Torah also sometimes
interchanges כאשר הונף כאשר הורם ka'asher hunaf ka'asher huram like the חזה
התנופה ושוק התרומה. chazeh hatnufa veshok hatruma. So without going into all
his detail, he basically says תרומה truma like when you give תרומה
truma to a כהן kohen is basically you just designate something to
be given to God; that's תרומה. truma. So therefore it could be
a verbal designation. תנופה tnufa is similar, but תנופה tnufa is always
לפני ה׳, lifnei Hashem, like we saw yesterday. So תנופה tnufa is
also a way of giving it to God but not through verbal
designation, but in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash through this act of
waving, of like, you know, raising up. He actually believes that תנופה
tnufa is not waving, it's actually waving up. Anyway, raising up, you're
showing you're giving it to God. It's a similar way of giving
it to God, but not through a verbal declaration. But the reason
he says תנופה tnufa is demanded and not just a verbal declaration
is because these are things that are given to God that actually
go into the Temple as opposed to like the תרומה truma that
you give to a כהן kohen doesn't go in the Temple. So
he says, what do you do תנופה tnufa for? Basically you do
תנופה tnufa for things that you fundamentally are not already fully designated
to God. He basically קדשים קלים kodashim kalim is more what requires
תנופה. tnufa. So the חזה ושוק chazeh veshok and whatever, you know,
the גמרא Gemara says that there's no מעילה me'ilah by קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim until you שחט shacht it and until—and except for the
אימורים eimurim because, you know, until then it's really all under the
owner's control. So you need this act of תנופה tnufa to show
you're taking it out of the owner's control and giving it to
God. So similarly a lot of—it works with a number of these
things; it doesn't work with all because the מנחות menachot that require
the עומר omer and the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, etc., those are
fully קדשי קדשים. kadshei kodashim. So there he tries to emphasize more
that they are, you know, that like what we said yesterday, that
they also play, that they're somewhat different and distinctive. Anyway his emphasis,
the פשט pshat of it without going into all the details, is
his emphasis is תנופה tnufa is the idea of giving from the
owner to God. And therefore the emphasis of the תורה Torah ידיו
תביאנה. yadav teviena. So the reason I bring all this up is
because according to his approach at least, you can't just say, "Oh,
תנופה tnufa can also be by the כהנים." kohanim. But according to
his approach, the whole idea of תנופה tnufa is showing that you're
taking your thing and presenting it to God and the whole emphasis
of the תורה Torah ידיו תביאנה. yadav teviena. So the גמרא Gemara
here does two things. The גמרא Gemara first of all reads into
the משנה, Mishna, which I think is very—questionable as פשט pshat on
the משנה Mishna although it has ברייתות—reads braitot into the משנה Mishna
that women don't actually do the תנופה, tnufa, but nevertheless is saying
that nevertheless it gets done. Why? Because in contrast to סמיכה, Smicha,
which is about—which is about ownership, תנופה tnufa can be done on
the—on the קרבן korban and it's a ritual which isn't about ownership.
Again in contrast to the idea that the whole point of תנופה
tnufa is to show that you're giving it over to God. So
that's—anyway what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Of course and it is
problematic—it is disturbing, this whole thing about excluding women, and it does
also seem interesting that, you know, whenever it comes like with women
having like this direct contact with the קרבן korban in some type
of a ritual. ritual, you know, that's where they're being excluded. There
just seems to be a common denominator between the סמיכה Semicha and
the תנופה. Tnupha.
So עוף Oaf and חמץ Chametz not do תנופה, Tnupha, right? What?
עוף Oaf and חמץ Chametz not do תנופה, Tnupha, right? Correct. Does
it if it's all identifying it as your קרבן, Korban, why not?
Again, it seems that—but why wouldn't they do it if it's all
identifying with your קרבן?
Korban? Women are permitted, they're not obligated.
Well, that's right, that's a debate in the תנאים Tannaim whether they
would be allowed.
So that we don't see because it only
identifies up as the כהנים, Kohanim,
right, right, we don't see that. Right. But why are they not
allowed to, though? If it's supposed to identify you.
Even where Rivka says that women were permitted is debated in the
גמרא, Gemara, it's debated in the—you know, it's debated in the ברייתא,
Baraitha, it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. So I also think there's
just some sense here about like, you know, who has access and
who really plays a—you know, and who directly comes in contact, even
though you accept the קרבנות, Korbanot, let's face it, there was an
עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, which was saying that not that women can't
go into the מקדש, Mikdash, but that they were—their place was primarily
seen as out of it. You know, עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim in
contrast to the עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. You have exactly that contrast
of ישראל Yisrael and נשים Nashim here. So I think that, you
know, I think it is reflecting this idea that women's access is,
you know, limited. So they can bring a קרבן, Korban, but, you
know, that they're
primarily—they're not seen as primarily present in the עזרה Azara and they're
not seen as, you know, sort of directly playing a role in
the bringing of the קרבן. Korban. So I mean, I think that's
what's being reflected in this text. I don't see another way of
reading it. I mean, Rivka, do you have something you want to
share about that?
No, I'm just thinking about the repercussions that this attitude has had
over the ages and even now, should we ever renew some sort
of, you know, Temple? Right.
Women are going to be excluded again.
Well, yeah, and when I talk about the מחיצה, Mechitza, by the
way, I point out that one of the models of מחיצה Mechitza
is עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, but that's actually a deeply problematic model
of the מקדש. Mikdash. That's a deeply problematic model. The other models
as well to explain why we have that problematic model, basically says
women's place is not in the sanctuary. Like the whole idea of
an עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim is that it's not the fundamental מקום
עבודה. makom avoda. And I actually was giving this talk once, and
a woman said, you know, that's so fascinating because in my שול
Shul there's all these discussions about, you know, where the מחיצה Mechitza
or whatever, right now it's in the back and there were people
saying let's move it at least to the side, you know, not
down the middle, but whatever, you know, along the side, the margins.
And the rabbi said, absolutely not, it's based on the model of
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and the women's section has to be
in the back. So you know, there are repercussions to this. There's
no question. So anyway, so that's what we're saying. So we're saying
that the women don't do the תנופה, Tnupha, but it does get
done. So now the גמרא Gemara says: תניא אידך, Tanya Idach, we
talk another ברייתא: Baraitha: בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, the children of Israel,
אין לי אלא בני ישראל, ein li ela bnei Yisrael, גרים ועבדים
משוחררים מנין? geirim va-avadim meshuchrarim minayin? How do you know to include,
you know, converts and freed slaves, which are male and fully Jewish
now that they're freed slaves or they've converted? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar:
המקריב, Hamakriv, the one who brings it should do the תנופה. Tnupha.
או אינו אלא זה כהן המקריב? o eino ela ze kohen hamakriv?
Maybe it means that the כהן kohen who brings, who offers it
up does the תנופה, Tnupha, but it's not referring to the owners
in a more inclusive way even these גרים geirim and freed slaves.
כשהוא אומר: keshu omer: ידיו תביאנה, yadav tevi'ena, no, the beginning of
the פסוק pasuk says his hands bring. הרי בעלים אמור. harei be'alim
amur. You see you're talking about the owners and since it says
המקריב Hamakriv that includes even גרים geirim and freed slaves. תוספות Tosafot
here says, has a question: Do we normally need to include גרים
geirim and freed slaves? Don't we generally assume that they're included? So
תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, the גמרא Gemara is inconsistent about that. Look,
that's a general question: Are we normally assuming women are included or
are we normally assuming they're excluded? Are we normally assuming that גרים
geirim and freed slaves are included or are we normally assuming they're
excluded? So you know, this גמרא Gemara is taking a very narrow
assumption that basically we're assuming only naturally born male Jews. And therefore
we need to include גרים geirim and freed slaves and we don't
include women. Okay, so then the גמרא Gemara
says: המקריב—no, Hamakriv כיצד? keitzad? How do you do this תנופה Tnupha
of the owners together with the
כהנים?
Kohanim? Where—where did the כהנים Kohanim get into this?
Because they don't—they weren't quoted in the earlier, you know, it's not
explicit how they get into it here, maybe because it actually in
the פסוק pasuk it says המקריב Hamakriv twice, so maybe that's what
it referred to. Or the גזרה שוה gzera shava of ידיו ידיו
yadav yadav to ביכורים. Bikurim. But whatever, now that we know that
the כהנים Kohanim participate, what do you do? כהן מניח ידו תחת
יד הבעלים ומניף. kohen maniach yado tachat yad habalim u-menif.
He said you have to put his hands underneath, which means physically,
you know, directly touching the owners on the bottom, the כהן kohen
is under the בעלים. be'alim. Or whether like תוספות Tosafot says that
maybe in different places. Either way, they both do the תנופה Tnupha
together. Now the top of ס"ב עמוד א': samech bet amud aleph:
כיצד עושה? keitzad ose? Now what do you do when it's coming
to not to something like an עומר, Omer, but whatever, שתי הלחם,
Shtei HaLechem, what do you do when it's coming to actually the
שלמים, Shlamim, the חזה chazeh and the
שוק shok and the אימורים imurim of the שלמים? Shlamim? מניח אימורים
על פיסת היד. maniach imurim al pisat hayad. You put the fat
on your palm of your hand, that's pretty disgusting, or whatever, messy,
I should say. וחזה ושוק עליהם, ve-chazeh ve-shok aleihem, and
the חזה chazeh and שוק shok on them, ובכל מקום u-vechol makom
and then you wave it like that. One wonders how it doesn't
flip off. Also, no, you do it directly on your hand. I
don't think so. I mean, I guess the question is the חציצה,
chatzitzah, and so it's supposed to be direct on your hand.
Is it בשרי?
besari? Yeah, because it's not done with a כלי שרת. kli sharet.
Because the מנחה minchah is done...
I know, but that's sort of the way a מנחה minchah is
brought. So this is, I'd have to check.
Anyway, explain why women are excluded, they have to touch each other,
the hands for
the כהן.
kohen. Oh, תוספות, Tosafot, maybe תוספות Tosafot suggested that, quoted ירושלמי Yerushalmi
that was bothered about that by a מנחת סוטה, minchat sotah, and
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi sort of has some answer, well, you know, it's
only for a few seconds, it's not a big deal, this or
that. It could be, it could be that that informed, you know,
חז"ל'ס Chazal's assumption that women were not doing it because maybe not
the basic assumption that they didn't want to see women doing תנופה,
tenufah, but they couldn't imagine a woman and a כהן kohen doing
תנופה tenufah together. That's a possibility, certainly. Doesn't address the סמיכה semichah
question, but it adds a bit about the תנופה. tenufah. Okay, okay.
So anyway, one wonders how this thing is not all going to
fall off, especially if the אימורים eimurim are below. Anyway, וחזה ושוק
עליהם ובכל מקום שיש לחם הלחם למעלה, vechazeh veshok aleihem uvechol makom
sheyesh lechem halechem lemalah, and if there is ever bread together with
the חזה chazeh and שוק, shok, the bread goes on top. So
היכא, heicha, where do we ever find bread with a חזה chazeh
and שוק shok of a שלמים? shelamim? You have bread with a
תודה, todah, but the bread doesn't get waved. So where do you
ever have bread with a שלמים shelamim that gets waved? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פפא במילואים. amar Rav Papa bemiluim. It's
if you look in the פסוקים, pesukim, it's explicit. By the מילואים,
miluim, you brought a שלמים shelamim and it says that you wave
them with the bread. So that's what we mean, when they did
it with the מילואים miluim the bread was on top. מאי טעמא?
mai taama? Now where do you get this idea that the fats
are on the bottom and the חזה chazeh and the שוק shok
are on top? אילימא משום דכתיב שוק התרומה וחזה התנופה על אשי
החלבים יביאו, ileima mishum dechtiv shok haterumah vechazeh hatenufah al ishei hachalavim
yavi'u, that the thigh and the breast shall be brought on, literally
on the fats shall be brought, so it means they are on
top and the fats are below, are below, להניף תנופה lehanyif tenufah
to do a waving. והכתיב, vehachtiv, doesn't the פסוק pasuk also say
את החלבים על החזה יביאנו, et hachalavim al hechazeh yevienu, bring the
fat on the חזה? chazeh? So one פסוק pasuk says one is
on top, the other says the other is on top. So how
do you reconcile this? אמר אביי ההוא דמייתי ליה כהן. amar Abaye
hahu demayiti lei kohen. We flip it, in
other words. Thank you. ההוא דמייתי ליה כהן, hahu demayiti lei kohen,
you basically, ממטבחיים ורמי ליה. mimatpachayim veramei lei. So the כהן kohen
brings it from the slaughterhouse, he's got the breast on the bottom,
the meat on the bottom, the fats on the top. That's one
פסוק. pasuk. Then he gives it over to the כהן kohen or
to the owner and he does it upside down and that gets
it reversed. Now of course, how come you read one, how do
you know which one you started or which one you ended with?
That's also.
What is it naturally on a cow, which is on top?
That's an interesting point. I mean, obviously the meat is on the
outside and the fat is on the inside.
So, what would that mean what's on top? I mean, depends which
way you're standing I guess.
Is it all the fats on? Anyway, you have fats on the
inside and the outside, here's how they drew. Well we're, okay, we're
going to see for the lamb,
I know, but hold off on that, we're going to see that
later, okay, that's coming up in today's דף. daf. No, no, I
don't want to distract us. It's coming up later in the דף.
daf. Okay, we'll see it in a minute. Okay. והכתיב, vehachtiv,
but there's a third פסוק, pasuk, וישימו את החלבים על החזות, vayashimu
et hachalavim al hachazot, the fats go on the breasts. So how
do you fit that פסוק? pasuk? That says it's the fat is
on top. ההוא דיהיב ליה לכהן אחרינא ואזיל ומקטיר ליה. hahu deyaiv
leh lechohen achrina ve'azil mekatir leh.
No, that's the third stage, after you've flipped it over to do
the תנופה, tenufah, then he flips it over to another כהן, kohen,
right, the other way to put it up on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
and there the meat is on the bottom and the fat is
on the top. I don't know. Let's finish the גמרא. Gemara. לכהן...
lechohen...
והא קמשמע לן, vehakamashman, speaking to you that בעינן שלושה כהנים, be'inan
sheloshah kohanim, you do it with three כהנים. kohanim. Actually you don't,
because since you're doing it together with the owners, you're flipping it
into their hand, you can have one כהן kohen do all the
flipping because the owners are helping him flip it each way. Anyway,
but the גמרא Gemara says anyway should be done with three כהנים
kohanim משום דכתיב ברוב עם הדרת מלך. mishum dechtiv berov am hadrat
melech. It's nice to do things and get a lot of people
involved, it makes it much nicer. What is the significance of which
on the top and which on the bottom? I really have not
thought about that. Look, I will say here is the difference. The
fats go on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So when you're going to the
מזבח mizbe'ach the fat has to be on top, because you want
to sort of slide the fat off and see the stuff on
the bottom, it would be too complicated to do it the other
way. חזה chazeh and the שוק shok go to the כהן. kohen.
Part of the reason as I said the other day, look, the
חזה chazeh and שוק shok are waved together with it, if part
of the idea of the כהנים kohanim is they're eating it like
the מזבח's mizbe'ach's eating, it's easier to say by קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim which it's all dedicated from the beginning, here it starts as
קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, you want to almost designate the חזה ושוק
chazeh veshok as a type of a fat, as a type of
a thing that goes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but then the כהנים's
kohanim's eating of it becomes the eating of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
that's I think conceptually what's being done. Obviously therefore you need to
end with when you're going to the מזבח mizbe'ach the fat on
the top. So that could explain why when you're doing the תנופה,
tenufah, you know, it somehow is reversed. Because in order to get
there at the end. Okay. Now, ושתי לחם עם שני כבשי עצרת,
ushnei lachmei im ushnei chavsei atzeret, the two loaves of bread with
the two lambs of שבועות, Shavuot, those also get waved. תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, we taught: והניף הכהן אותם על לחם הביכורים. vehenif hakohen
otam al lechem habikkurim.
So now we'll see your picture in a minute Michael, the כהן
kohen will wave them, the two lambs, with the bread of the
first bread, the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. יכול יניח כבשים על גבי
הלחם, yachol yanich kevasim al gabei halechem,
so maybe it says they go on the bread, maybe the lambs
go on top.
תלמוד לומר על שני כבשים, talmud lomar al shenei kevasim, so then
it says על שני כבשים, al shenei kevasim, another פסוק pasuk says
that you put the bread
on. Just like the fat and the
meat which goes on
top which goes on the
bottom the פסוקים pesukim, _psukim_ contradict so תלמוד לומר _Talmud lomar_ על
Al לחם lechem. הבכורים _al lechem habikkurim_ the lambs go on the
bread נשתקל הכתוב _nishtakel hakatuv_ very interesting phrase the פסוק pasuk. _pasuk_
is שקול _shakul_ is like is you know is ambivalent or it's
evenly weighed it's evenly weighted which way to read it but it's
like in the reflective you know the פסוק pasuk? _pasuk_ is itself
being multivocal is being sort of you know is is is being
evenly weighted in both
directions they flip them I guess it'd be too difficult is that
it well
before but
there's no stages it's not you have to get it to the
בית המקדש _Beit Hamikdash_ בחיים _bechayim_ and then get it to the
מזבח mizbeiach _mizbeach_
yeah right it's just one
process you do both ways maybe let's see what the גמרא Gemara
_Gemara_ has to say anyway the פסוק _pasuk_ is sort of is
you know evenly weighted ואיני יודע אם לחם על Al גבי כבשים
אם כבשים על גבי לחם _ve'eini yodeia im lechem al gabei kevasim
im kevasim al gabei lechem_ I don't know if the bread is
on the lambs or the lambs are on the bread מה מצינו
_ma matzinu_ so therefore we have to look somewhere else מה מצינו
בכל מקום לחם למעלה _ma matzinu bechol makom lechem lemala_ the same
way we normally find the bread on top אף כאן _af kan_
we'll see that in a minute לחם למעלה _lechem lemala_ here too
היכא _heika_ where do we find bread on top so we had
this just at the beginning of the דף _daf_ so אמר רב
פפא _amar Rav Pappa_ במילואים _bemiluim_ by the מילואים _miluim_ that it
says you bring the bread and you wave them together with the
fat and the breast then we said before that the bread goes
on top it's not exactly clear I don't even know if it's
clear on the פסוק _pasuk_ that you do that but חכמים chachamim
_chachamim_ understood that that was done so that then serves as the
model now that's all very lovely but it doesn't reconcile the פסוקים
pesukim. _psukim_ okay it might be that now you've solved your problem
but you haven't told me why the פסוק _pasuk_ one time says
one way and the other time says the other way let me
just see quickly what it says by the
מילואים _miluim_ yeah וחלת לחם שמן אחת ורקיק אחד מסל המצות אשר
לפני ה' _vechalat lechem shemen achat verakik echad misal hamatzot asher lifnei
Hashem_ so first it says ולקחת מן האיל החלב והאליה ואת החלב
המכסה את הקרב ואת יותרת הכבד ואת שתי הכליות ואת שוק הימין
_velakachta min ha'ayil hachelev veha'alyah ve'et hachelev hamichaseh et hakerev ve'et yoteret
hakaved ve'et shtei hakelyot ve'et shok hayamin_ so you take the fat
and the שוק _shok_ and then וחלת לחם שמן אחת ורקיק אחד
_vechalat lechem shemen achat verakik echad_ ושמת הכל על כפי אהרן ועל
כפי בניו והנפת אותם תנופה tenufa לפני ה' _vesamta hakol al kapei
Aharon ve'al kapei banav vehanafta otam tenupha lifnei Hashem_ so maybe because
it says it second there's somehow assuming that it means it goes
afterwards and it goes on top okay so that serves as the
model okay but it doesn't really reconcile the פסוקים _psukim_ okay so
רבי יוסי בן המשולם אומר _Rabbi Yosei Ben Hamishulam omer_ כבשים למעלה
_kevasim lemala_ no the lambs are going to go on
top why ומה אני מקיים על שני הכבשים _uma ani mekayem al
shnei hakevasim_
all
right you don't have any choice okay ומה אני מקיים _uma ani
mekayem_ all right I get it you don't have any choice ומה
אני מקיים על שני הכבשים _uma ani mekayem al shnei hakevasim_ what
does it mean on the lambs if the lambs go on top
להוציא שבעה _lehotzi shiva_ if you remember with the שתי הלחם shetei
halechem _Shtei Halechem_ the שתי הלחם shetei halechem. _Shtei Halechem_ and the
two lambs come almost as a unit but together with it you
bring another large קרבן korban _korban_ of seven lambs and two cows
and one goat or one goat and two cows or one cow
and two goats anyway that's the מוסף _musaf_ but that's like a
whole collection of קרבנות Korbanot, _korbanot_ that come with the שתי הלחם
shetei halechem _Shtei Halechem_ so the תורה Torah _Torah_'s emphasizing you have
all of these קרבנות Korbanot, _korbanot_ coming with the שתי הלחם shetei
halechem _Shtei Halechem_ but there is a unique relationship a specific joining
of the bread with the two lambs they're not linked to the
rest of those animals so therefore when it says על שני כבשים
shnei kevasim _al shnei hakevasim_ it's not physically describing you put the
bread on top of the lambs it means they're coming connected to
those two lambs and that's their relationship and not to the other
seven lambs that are brought okay which is a very reasonable פשט
_pshat_ so על _al_ just means connected it doesn't mean physically on
top it reconciles the פסוק _pasuk_ and then he's got the lambs
on top though okay so that's what he says להוציא שבעה _lehotzi
shiva_ חנני בן חכינאי אומר _Chanani Ben Chakinai omer_ מניח שתי הלחם
shetei halechem, בין
ירכותיהם של כבשים ומניף _maniach shtei halechem bein yarchoteihem shel kevasim umanif_
that's Michael's picture you put the bread between the thighs of the
lambs and you wave them ונמצא מקיים שני מקראות הללו _venimtza mekayem
shnei mikra'ot halalu_ therefore you satisfy both לחם על גבי כבשים _lechem
al gabei kevasim_ the bread is on the lambs because it's on
top of one thigh וכבשים על גבי לחם _vekevasim al gabei lechem_
and the lambs are on top of the bread because it's below
because the other thigh is on top of the other bread so
you squeeze it between the thighs so the גמרא Gemara _Gemara_ is
a little offended by this suggestion and the גמרא Gemara _Gemara_ says
like this אמר רבי _amar Rabbi_ so רבי _Rabbi_ responded what לפני
מלך בשר ודם אין עושים כן _lifnei melech basar vadam ein
osim
ken_ I know Michael we'll hold off the picture we're gonna do
the picture when we get to it we're not up to that
part yet it's like why I can't hand out hand out to
a class if you want them to be listening to you okay
anyway
so ומניף _umanif_ so right אמר רבי _amar Rabbi_ so רבי _Rabbi_
responded what לפני מלך בשר ודם אין עושים כן _lifnei melech basar
vadam ein osim ken_
you would never bring a you know a gift to a king
that way the bread between the thighs yeah that would not
be appropriate anyway
all right anyway לפני מלך מלכי המלכים הקדוש ברוך הוא על אחת
כמה וכמה _lifnei melech malchei hamelachim Hakadosh Baruch Hu al achat kama
vekhama_ you want to do this for God that's how you're going
to bring the bread אלא _ella_ here's what you do מניח זה
בצד זה ומניף _maniach zeh betzad zeh umanif_ you have one next
to the other and you wave them so they're side by side
not on top and bottom and על _al_ does not mean on
top or on top it means beside so that's how it could
both be על _al_ because על _al_ does not mean on top
על _al_ means side by side yeah so or it might be
your picture which we'll see in a minute let's first get to
the two
dots ומניף _umanif_ where were we so the גמרא Gemara _Gemara_ as
they've thought ומינה, u'minah, הא בעניין על ha be'inyan al doesn't have
to be on top. אמר ליה רב חסדא לרב המנונא, ואמרי לה
רב המנונא לרב חסדא, amar lei Rav Chisda l'Rav Hamnuna v'amrei lah
Rav Hamnuna l'Rav Chisda, so one says to the other, רבי לטעמיה.
Rebbi letamei. Rebbi goes according to his reasoning, דאמר de'amar who says
על בסמוך. al besamuch. על doesn't mean top, it means nearby. דתניא
ונתת על המערכת לבנה זכה, Detanya venatata al hamareches levona zaka,
you should put on the מערכת mareches which is like the column
of bread, this לבנה, levona, and you don't put it on top
of the column, you put it on the table near the
column. Okay, well that's what Rebbi says. So רבי אומר על בסמוך.
Rebbi omer al besamuch. You don't put it on the column of
bread, you put it near the column. את אומר על בסמוך או
אינו אלא על ממש? At omer al besamuch o eino ela al
mamash? Maybe it literally means on top? כשהוא אומר וסכות על הארון
את הפרוכת, Keshehu omer vesakota al ha'aron et haparochet, the פרוכת, parochet,
the curtain, will give shade on the ארון. aron. It doesn't, it's
not really over the ארון, aron, it's next to the ארון. aron.
הוי אומר על בסמוך. Havei omer al besamuch. על means nearby, it
does not mean on top. Although it's not clear whether that's a
good proof because to give shade, you know, you have a curtain
standing up and you have an ארון aron here, the shade goes
on top, you know, the shade is cast. But okay, that's the
way Rebbi reads it. And now Michael, you can show everybody the
ציור, tziyur, so you know. Okay, right, everybody, you have your picture,
which is you've got the bread, you've got the lambs wrapped in
the bread, right? Is if doing this for the שתי הלחם Shtei
Halechem is the point or he's trying to do this for
the תנופה tenufa. of what? The שתי הלחם.
Shtei Halechem Okay, so you see, we've got, sorry, we've got the
picture about that they're on the side. I would imagine the bread
on one
side, the lambs on the other. This has it almost as a
sandwich with
the side of the lamb, side of the לחם.
Yeah, I mean the bread is 20 log, the שתי הלחם Shtei
Halechem is like שנים עשרונים, shnayim esronim, it's basically like, I mean
the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem. is like, I think like whatever, like
10 pounds of flour per bread I think. So anyway, they're not
little loaves, they're big,
plus the weight of the animal.
Right, plus the weight of the animal, right.
I mean I bet that's
that artist's imagination, but it could be just side by side like
this, right? Okay.
The lambs are just lying there so happily.
They're almost smiling and not moving.
You know, you put a little Valium in their feed beforehand, that
would
solve all the problems, just a little Valium. Okay, so anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we do the act of תנופה.
tenufa So מוליך ומביא מעלה ומוריד. molic u'mevi ma'ale u'morid. You go
forward, you know, back and forth, up and down. So back and
forth could by the way mean like this, but it could also
mean back and forth like in both, you know, in both directions,
along back and forth left and right, and then also there's the
up and the down. They get this basically from the idea of
תנופה tenufa and תרומה. teruma. They assume that תנופה tenufa and תרומה
teruma always come together. Sometimes the תורה talks about one, sometimes the
other, and they consider תרומה teruma means to lift up, so it's
up and down, and תנופה tenufa means to wave, and to wave,
as
so let's take a look. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן מוליך ומביא למי שהרוחות שלו, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan molic u'mevi lemi she-haruchot shelo, you bring it back and
forth, you know, to emphasizing things that move back and forth, wind,
to God who the wind is His. ומעלה ומוריד למי שהשמים והארץ
שלו, Uma'ale u'morid lemi she-hashamayim ve-ha'aretz shelo,
and up and down because of the heavens and earth. So basically,
it's a way of giving it to God, which fits by the
way what I was telling you with Milgrom that he sees the
basic whole point of תנופה tenufa, is this way of taking something
that was yours, that's not קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim yet, and you
know, fully giving it over to God. Again, it doesn't really what?
Literally giving, well it's not clear here if they said six or
if they said four. But anyway, but right now we're not, we're
just talking about this and this, it's not clear whether in the
this motion we're talking about both directions,
or also back and you know, behind. Right.
We're not fully spelling it out. Okay, but anyway the point is
for him conceptually, it's just a way of saying I'm giving this
to God. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara however changes it and gets
it closer to what we at least are familiar with with conceptually
about לולב. lulav. Let's take a look. דמערבא מתנו הכי, Dema'arava matnu
hachi,
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael here's what they taught. אמר רבי חמא
בר עוקבא אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא מוליך ומביא, Amar Rabbi Chama
bar Ukva amar Rabbi Yose bar-Rabbi Chanina molic u'mevi, why do you
do back and forth? Yes it is about wind, but not just
showing you're giving it to God, but כדי לעצור רוחות רעות, kedei
latzor ruchot ra'ot, to stop the bad winds. מעלה ומוריד, Ma'ale u'morid,
up and down, כדי לעצור טללים רעים, kedei latzor tlalim ra'im, to
stop the bad rains. Oh, who would that so, yeah, because you
get the wrong time, sometimes it rains, well I'm not saying it's
גשם, geshem, I mean
you're saying it is גשם geshem versus actual טל? tal?
Right, you're right, טללים tlalim literally here means טל tal normally means
dew, but טללים tlalim I think means rains or whatever, it means
any precipitation basically.
Okay. So אמר רבי יוסי ברבי אבין זאת אומרת שיירי מצוה מעכבין
את הפורעניות. Amar Rabbi Yose bar-Rabbi Avin zot omeret she'arei mitzvah me'akvin
et hapuranuyot. From this we learn that even things that are like
the remnant of the מצוה, mitzvah, you know, you're יוצא yotze the
קרבן korban without doing the תנופה, tenufa but even these things that
are somehow just, you know, making the קרבן Korban full, it's in
the phrase שיירי מנחה, sharei mincha, that's enough to prevent bad things
from happening. Are they? Okay. Hold on, let me read a little
bit. דהתנופה שיירי מצוה היא, De-hatnufa she'arei mitzvah hi, right it is,
that תנופה tenufa is just a remnant of a מצוה mitzvah as
it were, it's not required to be יוצא, yotze, ועוצרת רוחות רעות
וטללים רעים, ve'otzeret ruchot ra'ot ve-tlalim ra'im, and it stops the bad
winds and the bad rains. So Michael is right of course, it's
an important tell you an important thing about even the small things
matter and they make a big difference. The other thing I think
that is fascinating is again, it's hard to see, I think there's
a reason that the גמרא Gemara waited to have this discussion after
it introduced the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, because it doesn't really fit
like
the
תנופה Tenufa that...
It seems much more it
makes sense in the context of the שתי הלחם and the עומר
Omer which are right agricultural sacrifices. So they're not only thanking God,
but one also understands with הודאה hoda'ah there's always a subtext of
בקשה. bakashah. It's like when your kids say thank you, whatever. So
anyway there's always a subtext you're just thanking God but there's also
a sense of a prayer for future success and that there it
would be tied in to this idea. What I do think is
interesting is if גמרא Gemara focuses on preventing the negative rather than
asking for the positive. Why don't you say that you're doing this
to show that you want good wind and you're doing this to
show that you want good rain? Why is it interpreted as this
preventative role? And I really don't know the answer to that.
It's even worse that women are excluded according to this if the
whole details help the people.
Right, but nobody there's no owner for the קרבן Korban. for the
שתי הלחם and the עומר. Omer. There's no owner doing it. There's
only כהנים Kohanim doing it, right? Because those are communal sacrifices.
So here the כהנים Kohanim do it
without any owner, just by themselves. The only thing women were excluded
from were the personal קרבנות, korbanos which was the שלמים, Shelamim, the
waving. But these are communal קרבנות, korbanos so there's no owner. It's
only כהנים. Kohanim. The exclusion of the women were from the שלמים,
Shelamim, the personal קרבן. Okay.
The other thing about this is it sounds so like pagan.
You mean particularly the emphasis on preventing the negative? Yeah, I agree.
Meaning, not just like don't we want the positive more than prevent
the negative, but they often see like it's almost the sense of
like a ritual that stops bad things.
Exactly. Exactly. Yeah, like that whole idea of warding off evil as
opposed to a בקשה bakashah for success. I agree. I do find
it
strange and funny and a little disturbing that it is emphasized in
the negative.
Okay. So now the גמרא says, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, וכן לולב,
v'chen Lulav,
you do the same with your לולב. Lulav. You wave it in
the same directions, and he doesn't spell it out, but the implication
also seems clear. That's the other agricultural holiday. That's also when we
start saying
משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם, Mashiv haruach umorid hagashem, or say the בקשה
bakashah of גשמים. Geshamim. So he says you do the same by
לולב Lulav and presumably with the same results.
We get that from here? Where we get the תנופה Tenufa of
לולב? Lulav? I mean this is the model for לולב. Lulav.
Yeah, exactly. Of course. Right. So we never find תנופה by לולב.
Lulav. Now it also might explain why it's emphasized in the negative,
because it's in סוכות Sukkot time where we actually have a בקשה
bakashah for גשמים. Geshamim. The rest of the year, by the time
that you get to פסח Pesach and שבועות, Shavuot, you don't really
need the rain. You're more just you don't want the rain to
somehow be you don't want there to be a flood or something.
So maybe it's a time of the year where the concerns are
more about the negative than about the need for the positive. But
nevertheless, it doesn't fully answer the question, I acknowledge. Okay, רב אחא
בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov ממטי ליה. mamti lei. So now
we're going to talk about how רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha
bar Yaakov not about his שתי הלחם or his עומר, Omer, but
how he did his לולב. Lulav. Okay, so ממטי ליה ומייתי ליה,
mamti lei umayti lei, he took it out and he brought it
in, ומחוי הכי, umachvei hachi, and he demonstrated the following or said
the
following, ואמר, v'amar, גירי בעיניה דשטנא, giri be'einei d'sitna, an arrow in
the eyes of the שטן. Satan. So presumably, when he did the
up and the down, he more did like a jabbing motion and
it was like, that's for you, שטן. Satan. So it's like he's
trying to stab the שטן. Satan. So talk about concerns about like
evil forces, right? It's not exactly a תפילה Tefillah as much as
it is to attack the evil forces.
Presumably. What's not clear. The גמרא says ומחוי הכי. umachvei hachi. It
does say ואמר, v'amar, he said, but he seemed to be now
he said but he demonstrated, meaning he did it with the following
motion. ולאו מילתא היא, V'lav milta hi, the גמרא says that's not
the way you should be doing it, משום דאתי לאיגרויי ביה, mishum
d'ati l'igruyei bei, you're going to get the שטן Satan angry instead
of getting him you don't want you don't want to incite the
שטן. Satan. Now the more fundamental reason not to do it, just
you don't want to incite the שטן. Satan.
And רוח רעה ruach ra'ah sounds like something demonic anyway.
Oh, that's a good point, that רוח רעה ruach ra'ah here
it seemed to be a very literal meaning. But you're right, the
רוח רעה ruach ra'ah is like the spirits.
And the גמרא that talks about doing נטילת ידים Netilat Yadayim because
of the רוח רעה, ruach ra'ah, you're right, it does have that
whole I hadn't thought about that, but tying into that sense of
the evil and the demonic, that's an interesting point. Yeah. Okay, תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabanan, זבחי שלמי ציבור Zivchei shalmei tzibbur טעונין תנופה לאחר
שחיטה. te'unin tenufah l'achar shechitah. So the communal שלמים, Shelamim, there's only
one communal שלמים, Shelamim, which is the שני כבשים shnei kevasim, that
come with the שתי הלחם. Okay, so you wave them after you
slaughter them. Now we already know that you wave them before you
slaughter them, that was in the פסוקים, that's what we were talking
about until now, that you wave these lambs together with the bread.
Now we're saying after you slaughter the lamb, you also do another
waving, that's not in the
פסוקים. Okay, ותנופתם כמות שהן, v'tenufatam kemot shehen, and you slaughter them
the way they are, meaning
the full animal. You wave them the way they are, the full
animal.
דברי רבי, Divrei Rabbi, before you cut it up, correct.
Okay, and the חכמים say no, בחזה ושוק, b'chaze v'shok,
after you slaughter it, you only do the waving with the breast
and the thigh, not with the whole animal, like you normally do
a waving. Now, the funny thing about it, we'll see in a
minute what you learn out from, but obviously the funny thing is,
there's a reason you do the breast and the thigh with a
normal שלמים, shlamim, because then the כהן kohen gets it. There's something
that makes that distinctive. The מזבח gets the חלב chelev and the
כהן kohen gets the breast and the thigh. Here by the שתי
הלחם, by the שני כבשים, shnei kevasim? the כהנים kohanim are eating
the whole thing. There's nothing distinctive about the חזה ושוק, chaze v'shok,
which makes this position very strange.
So let's take a look. You have like this bloody animal you're
putting it on the bread? I mean, yeah.
Okay, well you try to put it on the outside presumably, maybe
you rinse it off. Okay, so במאי קמיפלגי, b'mai kamifligi, what are
they debating? So אמר ליה רב חסדא לרב המנונא Amar lei Rav
Chisda le-Rav Hamnuna, ואמרי לה רב המנונא לרב חסדא, ve'amri lah Rav
Hamnuna le-Rav Chisda, so one said to the other, בדון מינה ומינה
ובדון מינה ואוקי באתרה קמיפלגי, b'don minah u'minah u'b'don minah v'okei b'asrah
kamifligi, a great sort of methodological, you know, sort of hermeneutic question.
When you learn a- from- when you have two cases, A and
B, and you learn some fact about- some- some- something from B
and apply it to A, so when you apply it to A,
do you then put it fully in the context of A, or
do you maintain the original context in B? And we'll see how
that means in a minute, but that's what the phrases mean. דון
מינה ומינה don minah u'minah means learn from it and from it,
meaning take it with its context. דון מינה ואוקי באתרה don minah
v'okei b'asrah means to learn from it, but then put it in
its new home. You know, then apply the context of the new
place that you're applying it to. So here's going to be, let's
see how that plays out.
Okay, קמיפלגי. kamifligi. רבנן סברי דון מינה ומינה, Rabbanan savri don minah
u'minah, so learn from it with its context. מה זבחי שלמי יחיד
טעונים תנופה אחר שחיטה אף זבחי שלמי ציבור טעונים תנופה אחר שחיטה.
mah zivchei shalmei yachid te'unim tenufah achar shechitah af zivchei shalmei tzibbur
te'unim tenufah achar shechitah. So the same way by a normal שלמים
shlamim you do a waving after you slaughter, here too you do
a waving after you slaughter. So that's the B. The B is
a normal שלמים shlamim you get waved. Now, now what do you
wave with a normal שלמים? shlamim? You only wave the חזה ושוק.
chaze v'shok. So the question is, we're going to learn from a
normal שלמים, shlamim, but are we going to take it with its
context or are we going to put it in the new home,
in the home of the שני כבשים? shnei kevasim. ומינה, so the
first thing is you use the original context. מה התם בחזה ושוק
אף הכא בחזה ושוק. mah hasam b'chaze v'shok af hacha b'chaze v'shok.
The same way there the only thing you waved was the חזה
ושוק, chaze v'shok, here too. ורבי סבר, v'Rebbe savar, but Rebbe disagreed
and he says no, דון מינה ואוקי באתרה. don minah v'okei b'asrah.
You learn from there, but you then establish it in its place.
מה זבחי שלמי יחיד טעונים תנופה, mah zivchei shalmei yachid te'unim tenufah,
so what do we learn from the normal שלמים? shlamim? That you
wave it לאחר שחיטה. l'achar shechitah. אף זבחי שלמי ציבור טעונים תנופה
לאחר שחיטה. af zivchei shalmei tzibbur te'unim tenufah l'achar shechitah. Here too
you wave it after slaughter. אבל ואוקי באתרה, aval v'okei b'asrah, now
that you've learned that, apply it in its current context. התם הוא
דחזה ושוק, hasam hu d'chaze v'shok, by the private שלמים shlamim what
you wave is the חזה ושוק. chaze v'shok. אבל הכא כמות שהן.
aval hacha k'mosheheim.
כמות שהן בחיים, k'mosheheim b'chayim, you do it the way they are,
like the same way you waved it when they were alive fully,
you wave it when they're dead fully. So Rebbe's position makes a
lot of sense, because in particular, then there's nothing distinctive about the
חזה ושוק chaze v'shok for the שני כבשים. shnei kevasim, Okay, so
that's what they're debating. A general hermeneutic principle of do you apply
the original context or do you apply the new context. Okay, top
of the עמוד ב. amud beis. רב פפא אמר דכולי עלמא דון
מינה ומינה. Rav Pappa amar d'kulei alma don minah u'minah. Everybody said
you learn from it and from it, meaning you take the original
context. So if you take the original context, why not limit it
to a
חזה ושוק? chaze v'shok? והיינו טעמא דרבי, v'hainu ta'ama d'Rebbe, here's why
Rebbe says don't limit it to a חזה ושוק, chaze v'shok, because
how do you interpret the original context? כי התם, ki hasam, yes
I will learn from a שלמים. shlamim. מה התם דבר שמתנה לכהן
אף הכא דבר שמתנה לכהן. mah hasam davar shematanah l'kohen af hacha
davar shematanah l'kohen. But what does the original context tell you? It's
not arbitrarily the חזה ושוק. chaze v'shok. The original context of a
שלמים shlamim is you wave the part you're going to give to
the כהן. kohen. So fine, that's what I'll learn out. You wave
the part you're going to give to the כהן. kohen. So here
I'm going to wave the whole thing because the whole thing goes
to the כהנים. kohanim. Very nice. רבינא אמר דכולי עלמא דון מינה
ואוקי באתרה. Ravina amar d'kulei alma don minah v'okei b'asrah. Everybody really
holds you learn from something and then you apply it in its
new context. So its new context by the שני כבשים, shnei kevasim
we know when you wave them live. So everybody should say even
after you שחט shacht it, you wave the whole thing. So why
not? והיינו טעמא דרבנן, v'hainu ta'ama d'Rabbanan, this is why the Rabbis
say you don't wave the whole thing, because you have a special
פסוק. שלמיהם ריבויהו. shalmeihem ribuyahu. It says when you wave the חזה
ושוק, chaze v'shok, it says you shall- this is what you shall
do when you bring- and Rashi says, what's the פסוק? את חזה
התנופה ואת שוק התרומה לקחתי מאת בני ישראל מזבחי שלמיהם. es chaze
hatenufah v'es shok haterumah lakachti mei'es bnei Yisrael mizivchei shalmeihem. So
therefore, since it says in the plural "their שלמים", shlamim it's coming
to include even the שלמי ציבור shalmei tzibbur that they get only
the חזה ושוק. chaze v'shok. Clearly Rebbe's position makes the most sense.
Not only does it put it in its new context, but it's
a waving of the entire thing that goes to the כהנים. kohanim.
So they learn out that the שני כבשים from a normal שלמים,
shlamim, not only is it waved when it's alive, but it's waved
even after it's dead. And that is a perfect segue into the
end of the משנה mishnah that says that there are some characteristics
that apply to some קרבנות and not the other, and this last
piece we'll just try to say why can't we learn one from
the other? So this will go hopefully very quickly. Let's take a
look. רבי שמעון אומר שלושה מינים טעונים שלוש מצוות. Rebbe Shimon omer
sheloshah minim te'unim shalosh mitzvos. There are three types of קרבנות of
which they draw on three מצוות. mitzvos. שתיים בכל אחת ושלישית אין
בהן. shtayim b'chol achas v'shlishis ein bahen. That each one of these
things gets two details but not the third. ואלו הן, v'eilu hein,
these are
they: זבחי שלמי יחיד וזבחי שלמי ציבור. zivchei shalmei yachid v'zivchei shalmei
tzibbur. and the אשם *asham* of the
מצורע *metzora*. Okay. זבחי שלמי יחיד *Zivchei shlome yachid* טעונים סמיכה *te'unim
smicha*, so a private one gets סמיכה *smicha*. סמיכה *Smicha* is only
by private קרבנות *korbonot*. Actually, there's one or two exceptions, but basically
it's only by private קרבנות *korbonot*, especially if the idea is about
designating ownership. חיים *Chayim*, you do it when it's alive. ותנופה שחוטים
*Utnufa shechutim* and you do the waving afterwards slaughtered, right? Because that's
the חזה *chaze* and the שוק *shok*. ואין בהם תנופה חיים *Ve'ein
bohem tnufa chayim*, there's no waving while it's alive. זבחי שלמי ציבור
*Zivchei shlome tzibur*, the communal שלמים *shlomim* which is the שני כבשים
*shnei kvasim*. So what do you do by those? טעונים תנופה חיים
ושחוטים *Te'unim tnufa chayim ushchutim*, you wave it alive and dead. We,
alive is in the פסוק *pasuk*, after שחוטה *shchuta* is what we
just discussed based on what we learn out from the other שלמים
*shlomim*. But ואין בהם סמיכה *ve'ein bohem smicha*, there's no סמיכה *smicha*.
It is a communal sacrifice. אשם מצורע *Asham metzora*, the אשם *asham*
of the מצורע *metzora*, the sin offering or whatever, the אשם *asham*
offering that it's his part of his purification. טעון סמיכה ותנופה חי
*Ta'un smicha utnufa chai*. You do סמיכה *smicha* because it's a private
קרבן *korban*. You do תנופה *tnufa* alive. That's what the תורה *Torah*
says. ואין בהם תנופה שחוט *Ve'ein bohem tnufa shachut*, but we know,
but we don't say you do a תנופה *tnufa* after it's slaughtered.
Again, it's an אשם *asham*, it's not a שלמים *shlomim*. So it's
one thing to learn out from the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* and
the שני כבשים *shnei kvasim* by שבועות *Shavuot*, which is a שלמים
*shlomim*. There we learn out you do תנופה *tnufa* even after they're
שחוט *shachut*, just like a שלמים *shlomim* of a private one. This
is an אשם *asham*, so we're not going to learn out that
you do תנופה *tnufa* after it's שחוט *shachut*. Okay. So now the
גמרא *Gemara* is just going to say, why don't we just learn
one from the other? ויהיו זבחי שלמי יחיד טעונים תנופה חיים מקל
וחומר *Vihyu zivchei shlome yachid te'unim tnufa chayim mikal vachomer*. Let's say
that a private שלמים *shlomim* should be waved even when it's alive
from a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. ומה זבחי שלמי ציבור שאין טעונים
סמיכה חיים טעונים תנופה חיים *Uma zivchei shlome tzibur she'ein te'unim smicha
chayim te'unim tnufa chayim*. Communal sacrifices, you don't do סמיכה *smicha* and
nevertheless you wave them when they're alive. So therefore זבחי שלמי יחיד
*zivchei shlome yachid* by a private one, שטעונים סמיכה חיים *shete'unim smicha
chayim*, that we said you do do סמיכה *smicha* when it's alive,
since it has that one characteristic that the other one doesn't have,
then why don't we learn out the other one? אינו דין שטעון
תנופה חיים *Eino din shete'un tnufa chayim*, so let's also wave it
when it's alive. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no. מיעט רחמנא גבי
זבחי שלמי ציבור *Mi'et rachmono gabei zivchei shlome tzibur* by the זבחי
שלמי ציבור *zivchei shlome tzibur* it says אותם *otam*, you shall wave
them when it's talking about waving alive. אותם *Otam* למעוטי זבחי שלמי
יחיד *lema'utei zivchei shlome yachid*, only they get waved alive, not something
comparable to them, not the private שלמים *shlomim*. So yes, you wave
the שני כבשים *shnei kvasim* when they're alive. You might say, oh,
there's another שלמים *shlomim*, the private שלמים *shlomim*, let's wave that one
alive? No, a פסוק *pasuk* tells you no. Okay, that's why we
don't apply that to a private שלמים *shlomim*. Now we're going to
try again. ויהיו זבחי שלמי ציבור טעונים סמיכה מקל וחומר *Vihyu zivchei
shlome tzibur te'unim smicha mikal vachomer*. Let's go the opposite way.
Let's do סמיכה *smicha* on the communal שלמים *shlomim*, on the שני
כבשים *shnei kvasim*. ומה זבחי שלמי יחיד שאין טעונים תנופה חיים *Uma
zivchei shlome yachid she'ein te'unim tnufa chayim*. When it comes to a
private שלמים *shlomim* that you don't wave them when it's alive, and
that way it's weaker than the communal, you don't wave it alive.
Nevertheless טעונים סמיכה *te'unim smicha*,
you still do סמיכה *smicha*. זבחי שלמי ציבור שטעונים תנופה חיים *Zivchei
shlome tzibur shete'unim tnufa chayim*, the שני כבשים *shnei kvasim*, the communal
שלמים *shlomim* that is more weighty and that you actually wave it
when they're alive, אינו דין שטעונים סמיכה *eino din shete'unim smicha*,
certainly you should do סמיכה *smicha*. So אמר רבינא *amar Ravina*, so
רבינא *Ravina* says no. גמירי שתי סמיכות בציבור *Gimiri shtei smichot batzibur*.
That no, our base, and it's actually what's nice about רבינא *Ravina*,
he says גמירי *gimiri* which is just we have our tradition, that's
the way it is, but he also reflects the idea that there
are some rules here. You know, that's always very troubling when the
גמרא *Gemara* says, oh, let's just learn this from this, as if
this and this each other's up, that's it's like, there's like maybe
some logic and system going on here and you don't just arbitrarily
apply everything because one is stricter or not strict. They're different. So
anyway, that's to some degree what רבינא *Ravina* is saying. He's saying
that basically the rule is no סמיכה *smicha* by communal sacrifices. And
like I said, you know, סמיכה *smicha* is the whole idea of
establishing ownership. There's no real need to do that in a private
context there is, there's no real need or even ability, but not
even a saying need to do it at the communal level. The
two exceptions רש"י *Rashi* says are the פר העלם דבר של ציבור
*par helam davar shel tzibur*, right? When בית דין *Beit Din* rules
incorrectly. It says וסמכו זקני העדה ידיהם *vesamchu ziknei ha'eida yadeihem*, whatever
they produce the סמיכה *smicha*. But that's, you know, presumably to show
a certain sense of like, you know, not just ownership but like
responsibility
that they're, you know, they're taking the responsibility for, you know, for
what they have done and how it led other people to sin.
And the other example is, oh, obviously the scapegoat, the שעיר המשתלח
*sa'ir hamishtale'ach*. Okay, so there also, so what's similar in both of
those cases is I would say the sin and responsibility component. It's
not just the ownership. Okay? And therefore, so that's where, so there
it's really about a sense like you're transferring your sins in one
case in the, in the שעיר המשתלח *sa'ir hamishtale'ach*, and the other
I don't think it's as much a transferring but it's sort of
like, you know, it's sort of like when the זקני העדה *ziknei
ha'eida* go outside of the city by the עגלה ערופה *egla arufa*
as well. It's the leaders are taking responsibility and therefore those are
the two cases where you have it by communal sacrifices. Certainly not
on the regular, you know, מוסף *musaf* or יום טוב *yom tov*
sacrifices. There's no sense of doing סמיכה *smicha*.
I could have a bit of an arbitrary theory, you could just
easily make the case that the ציבור *tzibur* lack that they don't
have ownership on the קרבן *korban* and then the פרטי *prati* you
do the representatives of the ציבור *tzibur*.
You mean why, why do I assume that ownership is taken more
for granted if, well, because I think that if nobody is, is
represented... representing the owner and it's being done in the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash* it almost by definition it's this is a communal institution.
That's right.
Say the כהן *kohein* is representing the owner. Which owner? Whoever does
the the ציבור *tzibur*.
I understand,
but why do you need סמיכה *smicha*? Nobody is presenting themselves as
the owner.
But everybody is the owner. Of course.
I mean you
could be arguing
but I'm just saying there's no meaning if I bring a private
sacrifice, you can understand why my ownership can get
obfuscated. I'm this person I bring it, the כהנים *kohanim* then take
over, they're doing the whole thing,
I'm standing back there waiting for them to tell me that they've
finished it. Where's that sense that I, so you can understand the
need to underscore hey it's my קרבן *korban*, I'm the owner. If
you don't have if it's not a personal קרבן *korban*, then
then by definition it's communal. It's being done in the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash* communal. So I'm not so to say so I think
what I'm saying is two things. Number one is there's no other
way by the personal one if it easily be his ownership could
be lost. So therefore you need to underscore it or else it
could be just perceived as this is going on in the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. You know who brought it is totally out of
your it's at the periphery. Whereas by at the ציבור *tzibur* level
there's nobody there's no need to associate it. Right. So that anyway
right. Who else is it? Who else is it? I mean what?
Is it the personal כהנים *kohanim*? No, you know that he's playing
a functionary of this institution. This is a communal institution. So if
there's no particular ownership then it's assumed to be that's what I'm
saying. I mean besides the idea that what does it mean
to have a communal institution or primarily or personal right.
So that's interesting. You mean if you primarily sort of see do
you primarily emphasize that what goes on there is the תמיד של
שחר *Tamid shel Shachar* and the מוספים *musafim* and whatever and then
there's also an opportunity for individuals? Or do you sort of emphasize
that primarily it's there for individuals? That's interesting. Look, the reality is
also you did have an idea of the ציבור *tzibur* being with
their קרבן *korban*. You know, that was the whole idea of the
מעמדות *ma'amadot*. You had this representative from בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* in
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* to be but the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't
say because they have to do סמיכה *smicha*. It says because אין
אדם, אין קרבן נקרב לאדם אלא אם כן עומד על גביו *Ein
Adam, Ein Korban Nikrav Le'adam Ela Im Kein Omed Al Gabav*. So
presumably there was a sense to say we want you to represent
the ציבור *tzibur* for whom this קרבן *korban* is being brought. So
it's not like this concept is not possible. But anyway, whatever the
reason is, I'm just giving טעמי דקרא *ta'amei dekra*. Whatever the reason
is, it's saying we don't have communal תנופה *tenufa* except for the
שתי הלחם *Shtei Lechem* and in these two cases in particular it
seems to be underscoring that sense of responsibility. Okay, so let's just
finish it. ואשם מצורע טעון תנופה שחוט *Ve'asham Metzora Te'un Tenufa Shachut*.
So now the last one is is the אשם *asham* of a
מצורע *metzora* does not get תנופה *tenufa* when it after it's shachted.
קל וחומר *Kal vachomer*. מה זבחי שלמי יחיד שאין טעונים תנופה חיים,
טעונים תנופה שחוט *Ma zivchei shalmei yachid she'ein te'unim tenufa chayim, te'unim
tenufa shachut*. So the personal שלמים *shlamim*, you don't do the תנופה
*tenufa* when it's alive, you only do it when it's shachted. אשם
מצורע שטעון תנופה חיים *Asham metzora shete'un tenufa chayim*, אשם *asham* of
a מצורע *metzora* that you do it when it's alive. אינו דין
שטעון תנופה שחוט *Eino din shete'un tenufa shachut*? Certainly you should do
it when it's shachted. No. מיעט רחמנא אותו *Mi'at rachmana oto* גבי
שלמי יחיד *gabei shalmei yachid*. It says by the שלמים *shlamim* אותו
*oto*. You shall wave it. So it said so on the one
hand we do extend the waving after שחיטה *shchita* from the שלמים
*shlamim* to the other שלמים *shlamim*, the שלמים *shlamim* of the שני
כבשים *shnei kivsim*, but we do not apply it here to something
that's different, an אשם *asham*. It says it, אותו *oto*, only it.
למיעוטי אשם מצורע *Lemiyutei asham metzora*.
There is going to be something you do not wave after it's
shachted and that is the אשם *asham* of a מצורע *metzora* although
you wave it when it's alive. Okay. Last point. תנו רבנן: חמישה
שהביאו קרבן אחד, אחד מניף על ידי כולם *Tanu rabbanan: chamisha sheheviu
korban echad, echad menif al yedei kulam*. If five people are bringing
one קרבן *korban*, אחד מניף על ידי כולם *echad menif al yedei
kulam*. One person does the תנופה *tenufa* for everyone. So here you
have a sense of a partnership. Okay, and so you can sort
of bring a קרבן *korban*, a שלמים *shlamim* in partnership. Other things
you can't bring in partnership like an עולה *olah* but a שלמים
*shlamim* you can bring in partnership. And therefore who does the תנופה
*tenufa*? One person can represent the group. Why just five? Just as
an example. It's a group. Okay. והאישה, כהן מניף על ידיה *Veha'isha,
kohen menif al yadeiha*. Here again is a similar ברייתא *baraita* like
we saw before, not in the משנה *mishnah* but a ברייתא *baraita*.
If a woman brings it, there's an assumption she can't do it,
so the כהן *kohen* does it. Presumably also this helps justify why
a כהן *kohen* can do it. Once we've established the idea that
somebody can represent the group, we can also say that the כהן
*kohen* can represent the right, represent the woman. The problem is it's
not the same. It's that a member of the group in the
first case is representing the group. Here the כהן *kohen* is not
a one of the owners. So it's not it is a jump.
וכן השולח קרבנותיו ממדינת הים, כהן מניף על ידו *Vechein hasholayach korbanotav
mimedinat hayam, kohen menif al yado*. Similarly if somebody sends a קרבן
*korban* from מדינת הים *medinat hayam*, the כהן *kohen* can do it
על ידו *al yado* meaning for him. Right. So now you're moving
into this idea of שליחות *shlichut* of what he can do it
for him because you so the idea is consistent with what it
said about women. You know, if it was about סמיכה *smicha*, so
nobody's doing סמיכה *smicha* for the woman and nobody's doing סמיכה *smicha*
for the guy who sent his קרבן *korban* from מדינת הים *medinat
hayam*. But תנופה *tenufa* is seen not about ownership, it's seen somehow
as a ritual that stands by itself. Yet it involves the בעלים
*be'alim* but it's not require absolute their presence. So therefore תנופה *tenufa*
can be done, you can make your כהן *kohen* you know your
designee to do the תנופה *tenufa* for you. This big תוספות *Tosfot*
here which made our דף *daf* more manageable today has a discussion
of... Look, סמיכה *semikhah* is really important, and therefore says תוספות *Tosafos*,
how clear is it that you're allowed to send your קרבן *korban*
from מדינת הים *Medinas HaYam*? How clear is it that you can
bring a קרבן *korban* that requires סמיכה *semikhah* that doesn't have סמיכה
*semikhah* done to it? It's one thing to say by women since
they can't do it that it doesn't require סמיכה *semikhah*, but by
a man's קרבן *korban* if you're saying it requires, how are you
allowed to bring it לכתחילה *lechatchila* without doing סמיכה *semikhah*? In the
end of course he says we've seen you are, but he asks
a lot of questions where maybe from other גמרות *Gemoros* where it
seems that there's a real reluctance to bring a קרבן *korban* without
doing the סמיכה *semikhah* if and if the owner is not physically
present and doing the סמיכה *semikhah*. Okay, so I'll just say one
final comment by the way just not as for today's
דף *daf* but yesterday's דף *daf*, I was looking at as I
said Milgrom.
He has in terms of how he understands what these things are.
He has a very good פשט *pshat* in terms of the הגשה
*hagashah*. We were talking about the הגשה *hagashah* by the מנחה *minchah*
was the way I saw it was a type of almost a
זריקת הדם *zerikas hadam* particularly the גמרא *Gemara* emphasized the need for
the
יסוד *yesod*, also you could also understand it's a type of a
הקדשה *hakdashah*, I
emphasized sort of a מנחה *minchah* the emphasis of a כלי *kli*
as a הקדשה *hakdashah*. I was less thrilled with that. Anyway the
question is why you what the position of רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*
is that you don't do הגשה *hagashah* for מנחת כהנים *minchas kohanim*
that's fully burnt. Doesn't really work with either of my explanations. He
says he has a brilliant point. He says a מנחה *minchah* is
really a type of an עולה *olah*, right? I mean if you
look at the פסוקים *psukim* in the beginning of ויקרא *Vayikra* it
says if you want it from בקר *bakar*, צאן
*tzon*, birds and if you bring a מנחה *minchah*. So a מנחה
*minchah* is free will you're giving it as a gift, it's like
an עולה *olah*, but it's out of grain. You can't afford an
animal so you bring a מנחה *minchah*. What's the הלכה *halakhah* by
an עולה *olah*? You burn an עולה *olah* completely. What's the הלכה
*halakhah* by a מנחה *minchah*? Some gets burnt and let the כהנים
*kohanim* eat. So what he says is to sort of
demonstrate that it's functioning like an עולה *olah* and that it all
is deserving to be burnt you do this הגשה *hagashah* to the
מזבח *mizbeach* with the whole מנחה *minchah*. So you do the whole
מנחה *minchah* as הגשה *hagashah* in the מזבח *mizbeach* but it's thing
like
theoretically virtually it's all being placed on the מזבח *mizbeach*. Now that
it's all being placed on the מזבח *mizbeach*, the מזבח *mizbeach* gets
a piece and the כהנים *kohanim* get the rest but it's like
it's all going on the מזבח *mizbeach*. Again with this idea that
the eating of the כהנים *kohanim* is like the eating of the
מזבח *mizbeach* but that it's after you've demonstrated that it's all being
put on the מזבח *mizbeach*. So what's nice about that, he doesn't
make the point that I'm about to say. What's nice about that
is it dovetails very well with רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* that a
מנחת כהנים *minchas kohanim* doesn't require הגשה *hagashah* because if you're burning
it all you don't need to demonstrate. You actually are burning it
all. It's when you're not burning it all that you need to
sort of symbolize this and demonstrate. So I thought that was a
great פשט *pshat* in the הגשה *hagashah*. Okay we will.